<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: life | Nithin Saji]]></title>
  <link href="http://diadara.github.io/blog/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://diadara.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-18T01:30:38+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://diadara.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nithin Saji]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GSoC 2014: Monkey Project]]></title>
    <link href="http://diadara.github.io/blog/2014/04/28/gsoc-2014-monkey-project/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-28T23:20:01+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://diadara.github.io/blog/2014/04/28/gsoc-2014-monkey-project</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I applied for GSoC this year also and fortunately the folks at
<a href="http://monkey-project.com/">monkey-project</a> liked my proposal. My
original proposal was to work on a dashboard for Raspberry Pi using
the monkey webserver and the duda i/o framework built over it, however
my mentors asked me whether I would be interested in working with them
on another project. I was more than happy to say yes to them as this
represented a more challenging project which I must admit, a little
intimidating as I haven&rsquo;t had much experience in system programming
apart from making some system calls and the server client programs you
write in your computer networks course.</p>

<p>The project I will be working on involves creating a Lua plugin for
the monkey http server and also a memcached plugin for monkey-project.</p>

<p>Lua is an embeddable scripting language that can be used to add some
scripting capabilities to the monkey server. In addition to the usual
dynamic content creation, the plugin should be also able to do some
administrative tasks with the monkey server and also collect
statistics on the various api calls.The second part of the project
will be to integrate this functionality into duda as a duda package
and design a API for it.</p>

<p>The second project to be completed is developing a memcached plugin
for monkey that can can interface application with the popular
distributed in memory key value store database.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New year]]></title>
    <link href="http://diadara.github.io/blog/2014/01/02/new-year/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-02T00:10:22+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://diadara.github.io/blog/2014/01/02/new-year</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last year was full of ups and downs and I can honestly say that I am a
changed man.</p>

<p><img src="images/post/red.jpeg" title="Rehabilitated" alt="alt text" /></p>

<blockquote><p>You feel you&rsquo;ve been rehabilitated?</p>

<p>Red: Yes, sir.
Absolutely. I&rsquo;ve learned my lesson. I can honestly say I&rsquo;m a changed
man. I&rsquo;m no longer a danger to society. That&rsquo;s the God&rsquo;s honest truth.
No doubt about it.</p></blockquote>

<p>I have burnt a lot of bridges this year and created a few. I have no
regrets. One of the highlights of 2013 has been getting selected for
<a href="GSoC">http://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/homepage/google/gsoc2013</a>.
I had worked a lot to get selected and my acads suffered a lot because
of that. The whole affair proved to me that you could probably do
anything given time if you genuinely want to do it. I was also
disappointed a bit with the whole affair as I found myself losing
interest after sometime. I can&rsquo;t blame anything for it except my short
attention span. In the end I barely scraped through. Again I did
manage to learn a lot of stuff like python packaging, writing
documentation and some related stuff.</p>

<p>I have tried to learn at least half a dozen distinct languages this
year and picked up a lot of things. The lack of mastery is the only
thing that worries me. I have made it to point to focus on making
things rather than learning stuff from now on. Let&rsquo;s seen how that
pans out.</p>

<p>Another important change this year has been, switching to Emacs. One
thing I have noticed is how Emacs encourages it&rsquo;s users to look under
that hood and hack stuff. I you don&rsquo;t understand a particular key
binding or function just hit <code>C-h k</code> or <code>C-h f</code> and you will get the
docs with a link to the source. I am sure this philosophy of
everything is hackable will flow into the users day to day work flow.</p>

<p>Also I managed to read a few books last year. I certainly plan to
increase my book consumption  the coming year. Last year was pretty
disappointing with respect to TV. Breaking Bad and Homeland were the
only exceptions. Person of interest shown in intervals and that was
enough to keep me coming back every week though the lack of
alternatives must have been the main reason.</p>

<p>This year I had signed up for a number of MOOCs and only managed to
complete one. The one I managed to complete was BerkleyX&rsquo;s SaSS 1.
It&rsquo;s a pretty challenging course If you haven&rsquo;t done any rails
before.I learned a lot. I had signed up for the Scala course by Martin
Oderski, the programming languages course in Coursera, Andrew NG&rsquo;s ML
course, history of rock course on coursera, Georgia Tech&rsquo;s
Computational Finance and a few others. I had left them due to the
lack of time. Come to think of it I could have completed a couple if I
had concentrated my efforts. One more thing to change.</p>

<p>This year also saw Real Madrid and Arsenal both not winning anything.
Hope both do well this year.</p>

<p>So apart from the usual resolutions, the ones I hope to keep are</p>

<ul>
<li>read more.</li>
<li>code more.</li>
<li>complete some MOOCs(I have already signed up for a few)</li>
<li>contribute more to open-source.</li>
<li>master something.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
